<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The whole booke of Psalmes collected into English meeter by T. Sternhold, I. Hopk. and others, conferred with the Hebrew, with apt notes to sing them withall ; set forth and allowed to be sung in all churches, of al the people togither before and after morning and euening prayer, as also before &amp; after sermons, and moreouer in priuate houses, for their godly solace &amp; comfort, laying apart al vngodly songs and ballads, which tend only to the norishing of vice, and corrupting of youth.</title>
            <title>Whole book of psalms. 1614</title>
            <author>Sternhold, Thomas, d. 1549.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15195</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 2549.4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S176</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">21988452</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 21988452</idno>
            <idno type="VID">24926</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15195)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 24926)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1744:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The whole booke of Psalmes collected into English meeter by T. Sternhold, I. Hopk. and others, conferred with the Hebrew, with apt notes to sing them withall ; set forth and allowed to be sung in all churches, of al the people togither before and after morning and euening prayer, as also before &amp; after sermons, and moreouer in priuate houses, for their godly solace &amp; comfort, laying apart al vngodly songs and ballads, which tend only to the norishing of vice, and corrupting of youth.</title>
                  <title>Whole book of psalms. 1614</title>
                  <author>Sternhold, Thomas, d. 1549.</author>
                  <author>Hopkins, John, d. 1570.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16]+ p. : music.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the Company of Stationers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: lacking all after signature A.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms --  Paraphrases, English.</term>
               <term>Psalters.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:24926:1"/>
            <p>THE Whole Booke of <hi>Pſalmes.</hi> Collected into Engliſh meeter by <hi>T. Sternhold, I. Hopk.</hi> and others: <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred with the Hebrew,</hi> with apt notes to ſing them withall.</p>
            <p>Set forth and allowed to be ſung in all churches of al the people to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither before and after Morning and Euening prayer, as alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore &amp; after Sermons; and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, in priuate houſes, for their godly ſolace &amp; comfort, laying apart al vngodly ſongs and Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lads, which tend only to the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing of vice and corrupting of youth.</p>
            <p>Printed for the Company of Stationers. 1614.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:24926:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24926:2"/>
            <head>A Treatiſe made by Athanaſius the Great, concerning the vſe and vertue of the Pſalmes.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>ALl holy Scripture is certainly the teacher of all vertue, and of the true faith: but the booke of the pſalmes doth expreſſe after a certaine manner the very ſtate and condition of the ſoule. For as he which intendeth to preſent himſelfe to a King will firſt compound himſelfe to ſet in good order both his geſture and his ſpeech, leaſt els hee might be reputed rude and ignorant: euen ſo doth this godly booke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme all ſuch as be deſirous to lead their life in vertue, and to know the life of our Sauiour, which he led in his conuerſation, putting them in mind in the reading thereof, of all their affections and paſſions wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſoule is inclined.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moreouer, the pſalmes informe and teach euery man with diuers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, whereby he may not onely ſpy the affections and ſtate of his ſoule, and to winne a good paterne and diſcipline how hee may pleaſe God, but alſo with what forme of words he may amend himſelfe, and how to giue God thanks, leaſt if he should ſpeake otherwiſe then were conuenient, he should fall into impiety by his vnreuerent eſtimation of God: for wee must all make account to the Iudge, as well of our idle words as our ill deſerts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IF therefore thou wouldeſt at any time deſcribe a bleſſed man who he is, and what thing maketh him to be ſo, thou haſt the 1.32.41.112.128. Pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="2">2 If thou wouldeſt rebuke the Iewes for their ſpight they haue to Chriſt, thou haſt the 2. pſalme.</p>
            <p n="3">3 If thine owne familiars purſue thee; and if any riſe againſt thee, ſay the 3.143. Pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="4">4 If thus in trouble thou haſt called on God, and haſt tarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon his help, and wouldſt giue him thanks for that he hath heard thee with his help ſing the 4.40.116. pſalms.</p>
            <p n="5">5 If thou ſeeſt that euill men lay ſnares for thee, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſireſt Gods eares to heare thy prayer, ſing the 5. pſalme.</p>
            <p n="6">6 If thou feeleſt Gods dreadfull threats, and ſeeſt thy ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of them, thou mayſt ſay the 6 38.88. pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="7">7 If any take counſell againſt thee, as Achitophel did againſt Dauid, if thou be admoniſhed thereof, ſing the 7. pſalme.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:24926:3"/>
            <p n="8">8 If thou in beholding the grace of our Sauior ſpred on euery ſide, eſpecially for the reſtoring of mankind to ſaluation, wouldſt ſpeake thereof in meditation to God, ſing the 8. pſalme</p>
            <p n="9">9 If ſo againe thou wilt ſing in giui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g thanks to God for the proſperous gathering of thy fruites, uſe the 8. pſalme.</p>
            <p n="10">10 If thou wouldeſt haue thine aduerſarie, kept, backe &amp; thy ſoule ſaued, truſt not in thy ſelfe but in the Son of God, ſinging the 9. Pſalme.</p>
            <p n="11">11 If thou perceiueſt God to bee wroth with his people, as though he regarded them nothing thou haſt to pacifie him, to complaine thereof, the 10, 60, 74 pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="12">12 If any man would put thee in feare, haue thou thy hope in God, and ſing the 11. pſame.</p>
            <p n="13">13 If thou behodeſt the pride of many men, and ſeeſt malice to abound, ſo that there is no godi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es among men repaire then and ſing the 3 6, 21, Pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="14">14 If thine aduerſary lye long in wait againſt thee, diſpayre not as though God had forgotten thee, but call vpon the Lord, and ſay the 14, 55, pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="15">15 If thou heareſt any to blaſpheme God in his prouidence, be not partaker with them in wickednes, but make haſt to God, and ſay the 12. pſame.</p>
            <p n="16">16 If thou deſireſt to know who is a Cittizen of heauen, ſing the 15, pſame.</p>
            <p n="17">17 If thou haſt need of prayer for ſuch as be againſt thee, &amp; haue cloſed thy ſoule on euery ſide, ſing the 16, 17, 86, 141, pſa.</p>
            <p n="18">18 If thou haſt eſcaped from thine enemies, and art deliuered from them who purſued thee, ſing thou the 18, 9 pſames.</p>
            <p n="19">19 If thou doſt wonder at the order of things created by God, conſidering the grace of the deuine prouidence, ſing the 19, 24.</p>
            <p n="20">20 If thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eeſt any man in aduerſity, comfort him, and pray for him with the 20. pſalme.</p>
            <p n="21">21 If thou perceiueſt thy ſelfe to be defended &amp; fed by God, and to liue proſperouſly, reioyce therein, and ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g the 23. pſalm.</p>
            <p n="22">22 If thine enemies conſpire againſt thee, lift vp thy ſoule to God, and ſay the 23, pſalme and thou ſhalt eſpy them to labour but in vaine againſt thee.</p>
            <p n="23">23 If thine enemies cluſter agai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt thee, &amp; go about with their bloudy hands to deſtroy thee go not thou about by mans helpe to reue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge it, for all mens iudgements are not truſty, but require God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be Iudge, for he alone is iudge, &amp; ſay the 26, 35, 43. pſa.</p>
            <p n="24">24 If <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey preſſe more fiercely on thee though they be in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers like an armed hoaſt, feare them not which thus reiect thee, as though thou wert not annointed and elect by God, but ſing the 27. Pſalme.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:24926:3"/>
            <p n="25">25 If they be yet ſo impudent that lay waite againſt thee, ſo that it is not lawfull for thee to haue any vocation by them, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard them not, but ſing to God the 48, Pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="26">26 If thou wilt exhort and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouoke Kings and Princes to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit their power to God, &amp; regard his honour, ſing the 29. 82. pſ.</p>
            <p n="27">27 If thou renew and builde thine houſe, bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h of thy ſoule, whereto thou receiueſt God to hoaſt, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d of thy temporall habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, ſing the 30. 48, 127 pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="28">28 If thou ſeeſt thy ſelfe had in hate for the truths ſake of thy friends and kinsfolke, leaue not off thy purpoſe, nor feare them which be againſt thee, but thinke on them which follow, &amp; ſing the 31. pſalme.</p>
            <p n="29">29 If thou beholdeſt ſuch as be baptiſed, &amp; ſo deliuered from the corruption of theyr birth, praiſe thou the bountifull grace of God, and ſing the 32, pſalme.</p>
            <p n="30">30 If thou delighteſt to ſing among many, cal together righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous men of godly life, and ſing the 33. Pſalme.</p>
            <p n="31">31 If by chance thou falleſt amongſt thine enemies and yet haſt fortunately ſcaped them if therefore thou wilt giue thanks, call together meeke men, and ſing the 34, pſalme.</p>
            <p n="32">32 If thou ſeeſt wicked men contend among themſelus to do miſchiefe, thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke not that their Nature doth impell them by ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity to worke ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> againſt their will, as certaine heretikes ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, but conſider the 36 pſalme, and thou ſhalt perceiue that they be to themſelues their owne occaſion of ſinning.</p>
            <p n="33">33 If thou ſeeſt how wicked men do much wickedneſſe, and that yet ſimple folke praiſe ſuch, when thou wilt admoniſh any man not to follow them to be like vnto them, becauſe they ſhall be ſhortly rooted out and deſtroyed; ſpeake to thy ſelfe and to other the 37 pſalme.</p>
            <p n="34">34 If thou haſt decreed to take heed of thy ſelfe &amp; ſeeſt thine enemy approch nigh thee as againſt one whom the aduerſary, is more prouoked to come with aſſault, and therefore wilt prepare thy ſelfe, ſing the 39, pſame</p>
            <p n="35">35 If thou ſeeſt many poore men to beg, &amp; wilt ſhew pitty to them, thou mayſt both thy ſelfe receiue them to mercy, and alſo exhort other to do the ſame, ſaying the 41. pſalme.</p>
            <p n="36">36 If thou haſt a deſire to Godward &amp; heareſt thine enemies to vpbraid thee, be not troubed, but conſider what fruit of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality riſeth to thee for this deſire, comfort thy ſoule with hope to God, and ſo therein relieuing and aſſwaging the heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thy life, ſay the 42, pſalme.</p>
            <p n="37">37 If thou wilt remember Gods benefits which hee did to thy fathers both in their out going from Egypt and in the deſert, &amp; how good God was vnto them, but they vnthankfull to him. thou haſt the 44, 78, 89, 102, 114, 117. pſalmes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:24926:4"/>
            <p n="38">38 If thou haſt made thy refuge to God, and haſt eſcaped ſuch trouble as was prepared againſt thee, if thou wilt giue thanks &amp; ſhew out his kindneſſe to thee, ſing the 46. pſalme.</p>
            <p n="39">39 If thou wilt know how to giue thanks to God when thou doeſt reſort to him with ſound vnderſtanding, ſing the 47, 48.</p>
            <p n="40">40 If thou wilt exhort men to put their truſt in the liuing God, who miniſtreth all things aboundantly to good mens vſe, and blame the madneſſe of the world, which ſerue their God Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſo inordinately, ſing the 49, pſalme.</p>
            <p n="41">41 If thou wouldſt cal vpon the blind world for their wrong conſidence of their bruit ſacrifices, and ſhew them what ſacrifice God moſt hath requited of them, ſing the 50. pſalme.</p>
            <p n="42">42 If thou haſt ſinned and art conuerted, and mooued to doe penance, deſirous to haue mercy, thou haſt the words of confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the 51, pſalme.</p>
            <p n="43">43 If thou haſt ſuffered falſe accuſation before the, King, and ſeeſt the deuill to triumph thereat, go aſide &amp; ſay the 52. pſalm.</p>
            <p n="44">44 If they which perſecute thee with accuſations would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray thee, as the Phariſies did Ieſus, and as the Aliants did Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, diſcomfort not thy ſelfe therewith, but ſing in good hope to God the 54.57, 69. Pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="45">45 If thine aduerſaries which trouble thee do vpbraid thee, and that they which ſeeme to be thy friends, ſpeake moſt againſt thee, wherevpon if in thy meditation thou art ſomewhat grieued thereat thou mayſt call on God ſaying the 55. pſalme.</p>
            <p n="46">46 If perſecution come fierce on thee, &amp; vnawares chance to enter into the caue where thou hideſt thy ſelfe, feare not: for in this ſtrait thou haſt expedient words both to comfort thee, &amp; to put thee in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of his old mercy, with the 57, 142, pſal.</p>
            <p n="47">47 If thou wilt confound Hypocrites which make glorious ſhewes outwardly, ſpeake their conuerſion with the 58, pſalme.</p>
            <p n="48">48 If thy pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſuers commaund thy houſe to be watched; when thou art eſcaped, giue thanks to God, and graue it in the Tables of thine hart for aperpetuall remembrance, and ſay the 59. pſal.</p>
            <p n="49">49 If thine enemies cruelly aſſault thee, and would catch thy life, offer thy ſubiection to God againſt them, and bee of good comfort: for the more they rage, the more ſhal God ſubdue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſay the 62 pſalme.</p>
            <p n="50">50 If thou flyeſt perſecution, and getteſt thee into the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, feare thou not, as thought thou wert there alone, but hauing God nigh vnto thee, riſe to him early in the morning, ſinging the 63. pſalme.</p>
            <p n="51">51 If thine enemies would put thee in feare, and neuer ceaſe to lay traines for thee, &amp; picke all manner quarrels againſt thee, though they be very many, giue no place to them; for the darts
<pb facs="tcp:24926:4"/>of babes ſhall be their deſtruction, if thou ſaiſt the 61. 68, 70 71, pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="52">52 If thou wilt laud God with a pſalm or hymne, ſing the 65 66. pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="53">53 If thou haſt need to confeſſe God, ſing the 67. pſalme.</p>
            <p n="54">54 If thou wouldſt ſing to the Lord, thou haſt what to ſay in the 96.98. pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="55">55 If thou haſt need to confeſſe God with thankes, ſing the 71, 75, 62, 108, 117, 118, 136, 138, 139. pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="56">56 If thou ſeeſt wicked men proſper in peace, be not offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thereat, but ſay the 113. Pſalme.</p>
            <p n="57">57 If thine enemies haue beſet the waies whither thou flyeſt and art thereby in great anguiſh, yet in this trouble diſpaire not, but pray, and if thy praier be heard, giue God thanks, and ſay the 77. pſalme.</p>
            <p n="58">58 If they perſeuer ſtill, and defile the houſe of God, kill the elect, and caſt their bodies to the Foules of the ayre, feare not their cruelty, but ſhew pitty to them which be in ſuch agonie, and ſay the 29. pſalme.</p>
            <p n="59">59 If thou wilt informe any man with the myſtery of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furrection. ſing the 8. pſalme.</p>
            <p n="60">60 If thou wilt ſing to the Lord cal together Gods ſeruants on the feaſtiuall day, and ſing the 81, 95, 34. pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="61">61 If thine aduerſaries flock together on euery ſide, &amp; threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to deſtroy the houſe of God, and make their conſpiracies againſt thy Religion, let not their number and power trouble thee, for thou haſt an anker of the words of the 83, pſalme.</p>
            <p n="62">62 If thou caſteſt an eye to Gods houſe and to his eternal ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles, and haſt a deſire thereto, as the Apoſtle had, ſay thou alſo the 84. pſalm.</p>
            <p n="63">63 If Gods wrath bee ceaſed, and the captiuity ended, thou haſt cauſe how to giue thanks to God with Dauid, recounting his goodneſſe to thee and others, with the 96, 85, 116. pſalms.</p>
            <p n="64">64 If thou wilt rebuke Paynims &amp; heretickes, for that they haue not the knowledge of God in them, thou maieſt haue an vnderſtanding to ſing to God the 86, 115. pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="65">65 If thou wilt ſee and know the diſſent that the Catholike Church hath from ſchiſme, and wouldeſt conuert them; or to diſcerne the Church concerning the outwarde appearance and ſinnes thereof, thou mayſt ſay the 87, pſalme.</p>
            <p n="66">66 If thou wouldſt know how Moſes prayed to God, and in his meditation, recounting the brittle ſtate of mans life, deſired God to direct ſo his ſhort life that he might follow wiſedome, read the 90. Pſalme.</p>
            <p n="67">67 If thou woudlſt comfort thy ſelf and others in true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and teach them that hope in God, wil neuer ſuffer a foole
<pb facs="tcp:24926:5"/>to be confounded, but make it bold and without feare of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, ſing the 9 pſalme.</p>
            <p n="68">68. If thou wilt ſing on the Sabbaoth day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thou haſt the 92. pſal.</p>
            <p n="69">69. If thou wilt ſing on the Sunday in meditation of Gods word, deſiring to bee inſtructed therein, whereby thou mayſt reſt in Gods holy will, and ceaſe from all the workes and doctrines of vain men, reuolue that notable pſalme 119.</p>
            <p n="70">70 If thou wilt ſing in the ſecond day of the Sabbaoth, thou haſt the 95. pſalme.</p>
            <p n="71">71 If thou wouldſt ſing to the Lord, thou haſt what to ſay in the 69.98. pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="72">72 If thou wilt ſing the fourth day of the Sabbath, ſing the pſal. 94 for then when the Lord was betraied he began to take vengeance on death, and to triumph of it: therfore when thou readeſt the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peil, where thou heareſt the Iewes to take councell againſt the Lord, and that he ſtandeth bodily againſt the Deuill, then ſing the foreſaid pſalme.</p>
            <p n="73">73 If thou wilt ſing on Good-friday, thou haſt a commendation of the 63. pſalme, for then was the houſe of Gods Church builded and groundly founded, though the enemies went about to hinder it for which cauſe ſing to God the ſongs of triumphant victory with the ſaid pſalme, and with the 98. and 129. pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="74">74 If there be any captiuity wherein thy houſe is laid waſt, and yet builded againe, ſing the 96. pſalme.</p>
            <p n="75">75 If the land bee vext with enemies and after come to any reſt by the power of God, if thou wilt ſing therefore, ſing the 97 pſalm.</p>
            <p n="76">76 If thou conſideredſt the prouidence of God in his gouernance ſo ouer all, and wilt inſtruct any with true faith and obedience when thou haſt firſt perſwaded them to confeſſe themſelues, ſing the 100 147. pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="77">77 If thou doſt acknowledge in God his iudiciall power, and that in iudgement hee mixeth mercy, if thou wilt drawe nigh vnto him, thou haſt the words of the 101 pſalme. to the end.</p>
            <p n="78">78 If for the imbicil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty of thy nature, thou art weary with the continually miſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e and griefes of this life, and wouldſt comfort thy ſelfe, ſing the 102. pſalme.</p>
            <p n="79">79 If thou wilt giue thankes to God, as it is moſt conuenient and due for all his gifts: when thou wilt ſo do, thou haſt how to reioyce thy ſoule thereunto with the 103 and 104. pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="80">80 If thou wilt praiſe God, and alſo knowe how, and for what cauſe, and with what words thou mayſt do it, conſider the 113, 117 13<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6. 147. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>8. 149. 150. pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="81">81 I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thou haſt faith to ſuch thinges as God ſpeaketh, and belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt that which in prayer thou vttereſt, ſay the pſalme 116. to the end.</p>
            <p n="82">82 If thou feeleſt thy ſelfe to riſe vpward in degrees of well
<pb facs="tcp:24926:5"/>working, as though thou ſaidſt with S. Paule, I forget thoſe thinges which be behind me, and ſet mine eyes on thinges which bee before me, thou haſt the 130. pſalme.</p>
            <p n="83">83 If thou beeſt holden in thraldome vnder ſtraying and wandring thoughts, and ſeeſt thy ſelfe drawne by them, whereof thou art ſorry, then ſtay thy ſelfe from henceforth, and tarry where thou haſt ſound thy ſelfe in fault, ſet thee down, and mourne thou alſo as the Hebrew people did, and ſay with them the 137. pſalme.</p>
            <p n="84">84 If thou perceiueſt that temptations be ſet to prooue thee, thou oughteſt after ſuch tentations to giue God the thankes, and ſing the 139. pſalme.</p>
            <p n="85">85 If yet thou be in bondage by thine enemies, and wouldſt ſaine be deliuered, ſay the 140. pſalme.</p>
            <p n="86">86 If thou wouldſt pray and make ſupplication, ſay the 141, 142, 143. pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="87">87 If any tyrannous enemy riſe vp againſt the people, feare you not, no more then Dauid did Goliah, but beleeue like Dauid, and ſing the 144 pſalme.</p>
            <p n="88">88 If thou art elect out of long degree, ſpecially before other, to ſome vocation to ſerue thy bretheren, aduance not thy ſelfe too high againſt them in thine owne power, but giue GOD the glory, who did chuſe thee, and ſing thou the 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. pſalme</p>
            <p n="89">89 If thou wilt ſing of obedience, praiſing God with <hi>Alleluia,</hi> thou haſt the 105. 106. 107. 111, 112. 113. 114. 115. 117. 135. 136. 146. 147. 148. 149. 150. pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="90">90 If thou wilt ſing ſpecially of our Sauior Chriſt, thou haſt of him in euery pſalme, but moſt chieſly in the 25. 45. 100. pſalms.</p>
            <p n="91">91 Such pſalmes as ſhew his lawfull generation of his father, and his corporall preſence, be the 11. 69 pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="92">92 Such as doe prophecy before of his moſt holy Croſſe and paſſion, telling how many deceitfull aſſaults he ſuſtained for vs, and how much he ſuffered, be the 2. 129. pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="93">93 Such as expreſſe the malicious enemies of the Iewes, and the betraying of Iudas are the 21. 50. 55. 69. 72, 109. pſalms.</p>
            <p n="94">94 Such as deſcribe his agony in his paſſion, death and ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, be the 22. 28 pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="95">95 For his dominion &amp; preſence in the fleſh, read the 116. pſ.</p>
            <p n="96">96 Such as ſhew the glorious reſurrection of his body, be the 99 pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="97">97 Such as ſet out his aſcenſion into heauen, are the 93. 96. 98 99 pſalmes.</p>
            <p n="98">98 And that he ſitteth on the right hand of his Father, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>10. pſalme maketh manifeſt.</p>
            <p n="99">99 Such as ſhew that he hath authority of his father to iudge expreſſing his iudiciall power, both in condemning the diuell, &amp; al wicked Nations, are the 50. 72, 82, pſalmes.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="metrical_canticle">
            <pb facs="tcp:24926:6"/>
            <head>Veni Creator.</head>
            <lg>
               <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ome holy Ghoſt etrrnall God, </l>
               <l>proceeding from aboue, </l>
               <l>both from the Father and the Sonne, </l>
               <l>the God of peace &amp; loue: </l>
               <l>Viſit our minds, and into vs</l>
               <l>thy heauenly grace inſpire,</l>
               <l>that in all truth and godlines,</l>
               <l>we may haue true deſire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou art the very Comforter</l>
               <l>in all woe and diſtreſſe:</l>
               <l>The heauenly guift of God moſt high</l>
               <l>which no tongue can expreſſe.</l>
               <l>The fountaine and the liuely ſpring</l>
               <l>of ioy celeſtiall:</l>
               <l>The fire ſo bright, the loue ſo cleare</l>
               <l>and vnction ſpirituall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou in thy guifts art manifold</l>
               <l>whereby Chriſts Church doth ſtand</l>
               <l>In faithfull hearts writing thy law,</l>
               <l>the finger of Gods hand:</l>
               <l>According to thy promiſe made</l>
               <l>thou giueſt ſpeech of grace:</l>
               <l>That through thy helpe the praiſe of god</l>
               <l>may ſtand in euery place.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:24926:6"/>
            <lg>
               <l>O Holy Ghoſt into our wits</l>
               <l>ſend downe thy heauenly light:</l>
               <l>Kindle in our harts with feruent loue,</l>
               <l>to ſerue God day and night.</l>
               <l>Strength and ſtabliſh all our weakneſſe</l>
               <l>ſo feeble and ſo traile:</l>
               <l>That neither fleſh, the world nor Diuell</l>
               <l>againſt vs do preuaile.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Put backe our enemies far from vs,</l>
               <l>and grant vs to obtaine:</l>
               <l>Peace in our harts with God and man,</l>
               <l>without grudge or diſdaine.</l>
               <l>And grant O Lord, that thou being</l>
               <l>our leader and our guide:</l>
               <l>We may eſchew the ſnares of ſinne</l>
               <l>and from that neuer ſlide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To vs ſuch plenty of thy grace</l>
               <l>(good Lord) grant we thee pray:</l>
               <l>That thou maiſt be our Comforter,</l>
               <l>at the laſt dreadfull day.</l>
               <l>Of all ſtrife and diſſention</l>
               <l>O Lord, diſſolue the bands:</l>
               <l>and make the knots of peace and loue</l>
               <l>throughout all Chriſtian Lands.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Graunt vs O Lord through thee to know</l>
               <l>the Father moſt of might:</l>
               <l>That of thy deare beloued Son,</l>
               <l>we may obtaine the ſight.</l>
               <l>And that with perfect faith alſo</l>
               <l>we may acknowledge thee,</l>
               <l>The ſpirit of them both alwaies,</l>
               <l>one God in perſons three.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Laud and praiſe be to the Father,</l>
               <l>and to the Son equall:</l>
               <l>and to the Holy ſpirit alſo,</l>
               <l>one God coeternall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:24926:7"/>
               <l>And pray we that the onely Sonne,</l>
               <l>vouchſafe his ſpirit to ſend:</l>
               <l>To all that do profeſſe his name,</l>
               <l>vnto the worlds end.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="hymn">
            <head>The Humble ſute of a Sinner.</head>
            <byline>M.</byline>
            <lg>
               <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <l>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord of whom I do depend</l>
               <l>behold my careful heart,</l>
               <l>and when thy will and pleaſure is</l>
               <l>releaſe me of my ſmart: </l>
               <l>Thou ſeeſt my ſorrowes what they are,</l>
               <l>my griefe is knowne to thee </l>
               <l>And there is none that can remoue,</l>
               <l>or take the ſame from mee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But onely thou whoſe ayde I craue,</l>
               <l>whoſe mercy ſtill is preſt:</l>
               <l>To eaſe all thoſe that come to thee</l>
               <l>for ſuccour and for reſt.</l>
               <l>And ſith thou ſeeſt my reſtleſſe eyes,</l>
               <l>my teares and grieuous groane:</l>
               <l>attend vnto my ſute O Lord</l>
               <l>marke well my plaint and moane.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For ſinne hath ſo incloſed me,</l>
               <l>and compaſt me about:</l>
               <l>That I am now remeddileſſe,</l>
               <l>if mercy helpe not out.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:24926:7"/>
               <l>For mortall man cannot releaſe,</l>
               <l>or nuttigate his paine:</l>
               <l>But euen thy Chriſt my Lord and God,</l>
               <l>which for my ſinne was ſlaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whoſe bloudy wounds are yet to ſee,</l>
               <l>though not with mortall eye:</l>
               <l>Yet do thy Saints behold them all,</l>
               <l>and ſo I truſt ſhall I.</l>
               <l>Though ſinne doth hinder me a while,</l>
               <l>when thou ſhalt ſee it good:</l>
               <l>I ſhall enioy the ſight of him,</l>
               <l>and ſee his wounds and blood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And as thine Angels and thy Saints,</l>
               <l>doe new behold the ſame:</l>
               <l>So truſt I to poſſeſſe that place,</l>
               <l>with them to praiſe thy name.</l>
               <l>But whilſt I liue heere in this vale,</l>
               <l>where ſinners do frequent:</l>
               <l>Aſſiſt me euer with thy grace</l>
               <l>my ſinnes ſtill do lament.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Leaſt that I tread in ſinners trace,</l>
               <l>and giue them my conſent:</l>
               <l>To dwell with them in wickedneſſe,</l>
               <l>whereto nature is bent.</l>
               <l>Onely thy grace muſt be my ſtay,</l>
               <l>leaſt that I fall downe flat:</l>
               <l>And being downe, then of my ſelfe</l>
               <l>cannot recouer that.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wherefore this is yet once againe</l>
               <l>my ſute and my requeſt:</l>
               <l>To grant me pardon for my ſinne,</l>
               <l>that I in thee may reſt.</l>
               <l>Then ſhall my heart my tongue, &amp; voice,</l>
               <l>be inſtruements of praiſe:</l>
               <l>and in thy Church and houſe of Saints</l>
               <l>ſing Pſalmes to thee alwaies.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="metrical_canticle">
            <pb facs="tcp:24926:8"/>
            <head>Venite exultemus. Pſal. xcv.</head>
            <byline>T. S.</byline>
            <opener>Sing this as the Benedictus.</opener>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>O</hi> Come and let vs now reioice,</l>
               <l>and ſing vnto the Lord:</l>
               <l>And to our onely Sauiour,</l>
               <l>alſo with one accord.</l>
               <l>O let vs come before his face</l>
               <l>with inward reuerence:</l>
               <l>Confeſſing all our former ſinnes,</l>
               <l>and that with diligence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To thanke him for his venefits,</l>
               <l>alwaies deſtributing:</l>
               <l>Wherefore to him right ioyfully,</l>
               <l>in pſalmes now let vs ſing.</l>
               <l>And that becauſe that God alone,</l>
               <l>is Lord magnificent:</l>
               <l>And eke aboue all other Gods,</l>
               <l>a King omnipotent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His people doth not he forſake,</l>
               <l>at any time or tide:</l>
               <l>and in his hands are all the Coaſts</l>
               <l>of all the world ſo wide.</l>
               <l>And with his louing countenance,</l>
               <l>he looketh euery where:</l>
               <l>and doth behold the tops of all,</l>
               <l>the mountaines farre and neare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Sea and all that is therein</l>
               <l>are his, for he them made:</l>
               <l>And eke his hands hath faſhioned</l>
               <l>the earth which doth not fade.</l>
               <l>O Come therefore and worſhip him</l>
               <l>and downe before him fall:</l>
               <l>and let vs kneele before the Lord.</l>
               <l>the which hath made vs all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He is our God, our Lord and King,</l>
               <l>and we his people are:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:24926:8"/>
               <l>His flocke and Sheepe of his paſture,</l>
               <l>on whome he taketh care:</l>
               <l>This day if ye will heare his voice</l>
               <l>then harden not your heart:</l>
               <l>As in the bitter murmuring,</l>
               <l>when ye were in deſert.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which thing was of their negligence</l>
               <l>committed in the time</l>
               <l>Of trouble in the wilderneſſe,</l>
               <l>a great and grieuous crime.</l>
               <l>Whereas your Fathers tempted me,</l>
               <l>and tride me euery way:</l>
               <l>They proued me and ſaw my works</l>
               <l>what I could do or ſay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Theſe forty yeares I haue beene greeued,</l>
               <l>with all this generation:</l>
               <l>And euermore I ſaid they erred</l>
               <l>in their imagination:</l>
               <l>Wherwith their harts were fore cumbred</l>
               <l>long time and many dayes:</l>
               <l>Wherefore I know aſſuredly,</l>
               <l>they haue not knowne my waies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To whome I in mine anger ſwore,</l>
               <l>that they ſhould not be bleſt,</l>
               <l>Nor ſee my ioy celeſtiall:</l>
               <l>nor enter in my reſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="doxology">
               <head>Gloria Patri.</head>
               <l>All laud and praiſe be to the Lord</l>
               <l>O that of might art moſt,</l>
               <l>To God the Father and the Sonne,</l>
               <l>and to the Holy Ghoſt:</l>
               <l>As it in the beginning was,</l>
               <l>for euer heeretofore,</l>
               <l>And is now at this preſent time,</l>
               <l>and ſhall be euermore.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="metrical_canticle">
            <pb facs="tcp:24926:9"/>
            <head>The Song of Symeon, called <hi>Te Deum.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <l>WE praiſe thee God we knowledge thee,</l>
               <l>the onely Lord to be:</l>
               <l>And as eternall Father all </l>
               <l>the earth doth worſhip thee.</l>
               <l>To thee all Angels cry the Heauens </l>
               <l>and all the powers therein: </l>
               <l>To thee Cherube and Seraphin</l>
               <l>to cry they do not lin.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O holy, holy, holy, Lord,</l>
               <l>of Sabaoth Lord the God:</l>
               <l>Throughout heauen and earth thy praiſe is ſpread,</l>
               <l>and glory all abroad.</l>
               <l>The Apoſties glorious company</l>
               <l>yeeld praiſes vnto thee:</l>
               <l>The Prophets goodly fellowſhip,</l>
               <l>praiſe thee continually.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The noble and victorious hoaſt,</l>
               <l>of Martyrs ſound thy praiſe:</l>
               <l>The holy Church throughout the world,</l>
               <l>doth knowledge thee alwaies.</l>
               <l>Father of endleſſe Maieſty</l>
               <l>they do acknowledge thee:</l>
               <l>Thy Chriſt thine honourable, true,</l>
               <l>and onely Sonne to be.</l>
            </lg>
            <gap reason="missing" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:24926:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
